intimated that he, too, had a few words to say.
Like all of Napoleon's speeches, it was short and to the point.
He, too, he said, was happy that the period of misunderstanding was at an end.
For a long time there had been rumors, circulated, he had reason to think, by
some malignant enemy, that there was something subversive and
even revolutionary in the outlook of himself and his colleagues.
They had been credited with attempting to stir up rebellion among the animals
on neighboring farms.
Nothing could be further from the truth.
Their sole wish, now and in the past, was to live at peace and in normal
business relations with their neighbors.
This farm, which he had the honor to control, he added, was a cooperative enterprise.
The title deeds, which were in his own possession, were owned by the pigs jointly.
He did not believe, he said, that any of the old suspicions still lingered. But
certain changes had been made recently in the routine of the farm, which should
have the effect of promoting confidence still further.
Hitherto the animals on the farm had had a rather foolish custom of addressing
one another as comrade.
This was to be suppressed.
There had also been a very strange custom, whose origin was unknown, of
marching every Sunday morning past the boar's skull, which was nailed to a post in the garden.
This, too, would be suppressed.
And the skull had already been buried.
His visitors might have observed, too, the green flag which flew from the masthead.
If so, they would perhaps have noted that the white hoof and horn with which
it had previously been marked had now been removed.
It would be a plain green flag from now onwards.
He had only one criticism, he said, to make of Mr. Pilkington's excellent and neighborly speech.
Mr. Pilkington had referred throughout to Animal Farm.
He could not, of course, know, for he, Napoleon, was only now for the first time announcing it,
that the name Animal Farm had been abolished.
Henceforth, the farm was to be known as the Manor Farm, which, he believed, was its correct and
original name.
>> Gentlemen, I will give you the same toast as before, but in a different form.
Fill your glasses to the brim, gentlemen. Here is my toast.
To the prosperity of the Manor Farm.
>> There was the same hearty cheering as before, and the mugs were emptied to the dregs.
But, as the animals outside gazed at the scene, it seemed to them that some
strange thing was happening.
What was it that had altered in the faces of the pigs?
Clover's old, dim eyes flitted from one face to another.
Some of them had five chins, some had four, some had three.
But, what was it that seemed to be melting and changing?
Then, the applause having come to an end, the company took up their cards and
continued the game that had been interrupted. And the animals crept silently away.
But, they had not gone 20 yd when they stopped short.
An uproar of voices was coming from the farmhouse.
They rushed back and looked through the window again.
Yes, a violent quarrel was in progress.
There were shoutings, hangings on the table, sharp, suspicious glances, furious denials.
The source of the trouble appeared to be that Napoleon and Mr. Pilkington had
each played an ace of spades simultaneously.
12 voices were shouting in anger, and they were all alike.
No question now what had happened to the faces of the pigs.
The creatures outside looked from pig to man, and from man to pig, and from pig
to man again.
But, already it was impossible to say which was which.